Register of the Eric Hass papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Eric Hass papers
1899-1980
81034
Hass, Eric.
11 manuscript boxes (4.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, clippings, serial issues, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to the Socialist Labor Party, and to social problems of aging.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1981.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
1905 Born, Lincoln, Nebraska
1928 Joined Socialist Labor Party
1932-1938 National organizer, Socialist Labor Party
1938-1968 Editor, The Weekly People
1949 Author, The Socialist Labor Party and the Internationals
1952 Socialist Labor Party candidate for President (first campaign)
1956 Socialist Labor Party candidate for President (second campaign)
1960 Socialist Labor Party candidate for President (third campaign)
1964 Socialist Labor Party candidate for President (fourth campaign)
1969 Resigned from Socialist Labor Party
1974-1978 Lived in Costa Rica
1980 Died, Santa Rosa, California
Scope and Content of Collection
Eric Hass was a longtime leader of the Socialist Labor Party. This party, dating back to 1876, was the first Marxist political organization in the United States. A number of the early leaders of the subsequent Socialist and Communist Parties served their political apprenticeships while passing through SLP ranks. Even before the death in 1914 of its outstanding leader Daniel De Leon, the SLP had been eclipsed in size and influence by the younger Socialist Party. For decades thereafter it nevertheless maintained a low profile existence, regularly publishing its newspaper The Weekly People and securing a ballot position for its presidential candidate every four years. Hass figured significantly in these activities as editor of The Weekly People for thirty years and as a four-time presidential candidate. In 1969, however, he broke with the party. While remaining a committed socialist, Hass came to believe that the SLP had become intellectually stultified and internally undemocratic.
The papers of Eric Hass are divided. Many are located in the Nebraska State Historical Society. Those in the Hoover Institution Archives were acquired from Tillie Hass in 1981, after the death of her husband. These papers largely date from Hass's later years, following his departure from the SLP. After this rupture he worked for a time as caretaker of Trinity Churchyard in New York City, then retired to Costa Rica where the cost of living was low, and after a few years returned to the United States. As an experienced journalist and an avid amateur naturalist, he was able to supplement his income by writing nature articles for the mainstream press, principally the New York Times.
The Subject File contains a good deal of collected information on Daniel De Leon. The Speeches and Writings file includes some output by Hass from his SLP period, especially his editorial reports prefiguring his breach with the party, and his account of his resignation. The Correspondence file includes exchanges in the 1970s with Sam Brandon, Nick Simon and other former SLP members, analyzing their experiences and the prospects for reconstituting a De Leonist political organization.
During the decade of the 1970s Hass became increasingly involved in study of the social problems of aging, and in advocacy for older persons in regard to age discrimination and related issues. Toward this end he joined the Gray Panthers after his return from Costa Rica. Shortly before his death he completed a book-length study, "Agism: The Shunning of the Elderly." This manuscript, for which he was unable to find a publisher before he died, is in the Speeches and Writings file. The Subject File contains a substantial quantity of collected material on aging.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Socialist Labor Party.; Aged.; Older people.; Socialism--United States.
Collection Contents
- Biographical File, 1905-1980 (Folder 1)
  Identification documents, biographical sketch, curricula vitae, clippings, and medical and financial records
  - General, 1905-1980. (Folder 1: 1)
    Identification documents, medical and financial records, and miscellany
  - Biographical sketch, curricula vitae, and clippings, 1970-1972. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes press coverage of break with Socialist Labor Party
- Correspondence, 1930-1980 (Folder 1-4)
  Arranged alphabetically
  - General and unidentified (Folder 1)
    - 1958-1976 (Folder 1: 3)
    - 1977-1980 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Adler, Robert H., 1975-1977 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Alvarez, Jean, 1979-1980 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Ames, Gerald, and Rose Wyler, 1976-1980 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Ansello, Edward F. (University of Maryland Center on Aging), 1978-1980 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Bambiger, Barbara, 1972-1979 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Begovich, Margaret (re Socialist Labor Party), 1976 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Bergelon, Olaf and Rose, 1977-1979 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Brandon, Sam (League for Socialist Reconstruction), 1973-1980 (Folder 1: 12)
  - California. Commission on Aging, 1980 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Carter, Jimmy, 1979 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Church, Frank (U.S. Senate Special Committee on Aging), 1979 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Cranston, Alan, 1980 (Folder 1: 16)
  - De Leon, Bertha C., 1943 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Diamond, Julian (re Socialist Labor Party), 1976-1978 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Dorn, Sylvia, 1979 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Duranty, Walter, 1944 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Finger, Jack and Catherine, 1975-1979 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Folkerstma, Bote, 1971-1972 (Folder 2: 2)
  - Garamendi, John (California Senate Committee on Health and Welfare), 1980 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Garcelon, Dan and Peg, 1978-1979 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Gardner, Jiggs (re Socialist Labor Party), 1977 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Ginsberg, Arthur H., 1954-1977 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Girard, Frank (re Socialist Labor Party), 1971-1977 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Goodstein, Phil (re Socialist Labor Party), 1977 (Folder 2: 8)
  - Gray, Bill and Betty (Trinity Church, New York City), 1974-1980 (Folder 2: 9)
  - Gray Panthers, 1978-1979 (Folder 2: 10)
  - Hartke, Vance, 1967 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Hass, Tillie, 1930-1934 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Hass family (Folder 2)
    - 1939-1975 (Folder 2: 13)
    - 1976-1980 (Folder 2: 14)
  - Herder, Milton (re Socialist Labor Party), 1976-1977 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Landers, Ann, 1980 (Folder 3: 1)
  - Lazarus, Louis (re Socialist Labor Party), 1961-1976 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Levine, Max, 1974-1980 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Lewin, Ed (re Socialist Labor Party), 1976-1978 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Long, Robert W. and Helen, 1974-1979 (Folder 3: 5)
  - McClintock, Howard and Juanita, 1976-1980 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Maves, Gustavus A. (re Socialist Labor Party), 1934-1935 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Muncy, Ralph W. (re Socialist Labor Party), 1972-1974 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Nathan, Bernard, and Barbara F. Newman, 1974-1980 (Folder 3: 9)
  - National Institute on Aging, 1980 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Nebraska State Historical Society, 1973-1977 (Folder 3: 11)
  - New York Botanical Garden, 1969-1973 (Folder 3: 12)
  - New York Public Library, 1971-1972 (Folder 3: 13)
  - New York Times (Joan Lee Faust, garden editor; Peter Kihss), 1968-1977 (Folder 3: 14)
  - North Bay Health Systems Agency, 1979 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Northen, Rebecca T., 1973-1979 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Nunez, Margot (Trinity Church, New York City), 1974-1980 (Folder 3: 17)
  - Papernow, Leon N. and Felicia, 1976-1978 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Pepper, Claude (U.S. House Select Committee on Aging), 1979 (Folder 3: 19)
  - Perry, Benson (re Socialist Labor Party), 1969-1976 (Folder 3: 20)
  - Reeves, Martha, 1978-1980 (Folder 3: 21)
  - Reynolds, Verne L. (re Socialist Labor Party), 1934-1959 (Folder 3: 22)
  - Robinson, Jackie, 1957 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Samuels, Ed, 1974-1978 (Folder 3: 24)
  - Schwartz, Simon (re Socialist Labor Party), 1976-1980 (Folder 3: 25)
  - Sesame Street (television show), 1979 (Folder 3: 26)
  - Sherman, John (re Socialist Labor Party), 1968-1969 (Folder 3: 27)
  - Simon, John L., 1960-1980 (Folder 4: 1)
  - Simon, Nick (re Socialist Labor Party), 1967-1980 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Singer, Richard J., 1976-1979 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Skutch, Alexander F., 1972-1974 (Folder 4: 4)
  - Socialist Labor Party (Nathan Karp, Arnold Petersen, Emil F. Teichert), 1934-1977 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Stein, Philip and Sylvia, 1974-1979 (Folder 4: 6)
  - Stevenson, Adlai E., 1960 (Folder 4: 7)
  - Trinity Church (New York City), 1970-1975 (Folder 4: 8)
  - United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation, 1979 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Wexler, Arthur and Marion, 1977-1980 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Woodard, Jack and Lucila, 1974 (Folder 4: 11)
- Speeches and Writings, 1949-1980 (Folder 4)
  Arranged chronologically
  - "Why Labor Should Fight U.M.T.,", ca. 1949. (Folder 4: 12)
    Speech outline
  - "Daniel De Leon: Master of Socialist Tactics," speech, De Leon commemoration meeting, 1953 December 13. (Folder 4: 13)
    Typescript
  - "The American Double Standard of Living,", ca. 1954. (Folder 4: 14)
    Speech outline and typescript
  - Remarks at Belle Rosen memorial meeting, 1955 May 24. (Folder 4: 15)
  - Introduction to dramatized reading from Lincoln-Douglas debates, ca. 1959. (Folder 4: 16)
  - "Biological Demonstration of the Marxian Principle,", ca. 1950s. (Folder 4: 17)
    Speech notes
  - "The Meaning of McCarthyism,", ca. 1950s. (Folder 4: 18)
  - "The Paris Commune,", ca. 1950s. (Folder 4: 19)
  - "The Years of Capitalism Are Numbered,", ca. 1960. (Folder 4: 20)
  - Remarks at golden jubilee celebration for Arnold Petersen as Socialist Labor Party national secretary, 1964 (Folder 4: 21)
  - Report as editor of The Weekly People to Socialist Labor Party National Executive Committee meeting, 1966 May 7. (Folder 4: 22)
    Printed copy
  - "The 'New' Imperialism and War,", ca. 1966. (Folder 4: 23)
  - "On a Winter's Day: 'Twigging' Anyone?'" New York Times, 1968 February 25. (Folder 4: 24)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Survival of Giant Redwoods Hinges on Washington Report," Christian Science Monitor, 1968 May 14. (Folder 4: 25)
  - Report as editor of The Weekly People to Socialist Labor Party national convention, 1968 May. (Folder 4: 26)
  - "Nature's Botanical Oddity," New York Times, 1968 August 9. (Folder 4: 27)
  - "Wild Flower Protection," New York Times, 1968 September 29. (Folder 4: 28)
  - "Amy and the Deer Mouse" (children's story), 1968 November 12. (Folder 4: 29)
  - "Clowns of the Plains" (article for juveniles), 1968 December 13. (Folder 4: 30)
  - "The Living Fossil," New York Times, 1968 December 15. (Folder 4: 31)
  - "Another Mouse to Feed,", 1968 (Folder 5: 1)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "What's Wrong with the SLP?", ca. 1968. (Folder 5: 2)
  - "How Indians 'Talked' Without Saying a Word'" (article for juveniles), 1969 January 24. (Folder 5: 3)
  - "Oasis in the City," New York Times, 1969 April 6. (Folder 5: 4)
  - "Why I Resigned from the SLP," Socialist Forum, 1969 July. (Folder 5: 5)
  - "Benjamin Gilbert: Friend and Naturalist" (memorial meeting remarks), 1969 September 5. (Folder 5: 6)
  - "An Encounter with Winter" (written under pseudonym Jack Focht), New York Times, 1970 January 11. (Folder 5: 7)
  - "Jack in the Pulpit," New York Times, 1970 May 17. (Folder 5: 8)
  - "A Bonus for Woodland Wanderers," New York Times, 1970 May 24. (Folder 5: 9)
  - "House Finch," New York Times, 1970 August 9. (Folder 5: 10)
  - "Sharin' Erin's Floral Charms," New York Times, 1970 August 30. (Folder 5: 11)
  - "To the Irish Sea for an Eyeful of Puffins," New York Times, 1971 January 10. (Folder 5: 12)
  - "To the Rescue of a Tree," New York Times, 1971 January 17. (Folder 5: 13)
  - "Trinity's Yard Blooms amid 'Canyons,'" New York Times, 1971 April 11. (Folder 5: 14)
  - "'That Queen of Secrecy,'" New York Times, 1971 May 16. (Folder 5: 15)
  - "Yugoslavia: The Hinterland Also Seeks Tourists," Washington Post, 1971 October 31. (Folder 5: 16)
  - "Nature Haunts for Subway Riders," New York Times, 1972 April 2. (Folder 5: 17)
  - "The Old Apple Tree," New York Times, 1972 June 25. (Folder 5: 18)
  - Review of Alexander F. Skutch, A Naturalist in Costa Rica, Garden Journal, 1972 October. (Folder 5: 19)
  - "Block Island Summer,", ca. 1972. (Folder 5: 20)
    Typescript and working materials
  - "Hawking in Ireland,", ca. 1972. (Folder 5: 21)
  - Untitled article re St. Paul's Churchyard, New York City, ca. 1972. (Folder 5: 22)
  - "'A Small, Friendly Country that Fits Our Purse'" (re Costa Rica), Dynamic Maturity, 1973 January. (Folder 5: 23)
  - "Butterflies Are Coming Back to the City's Parks," New York Times, 1974 June 9. (Folder 5: 24)
  - "An Expatriate's Spring," New York Times, 1975 March 30. (Folder 5: 25)
  - "Our Outmoded Political Constituencies,", 1975 August 18. (Folder 5: 26)
  - "Report on the Fifth World Symposium of the International Society on Toxinology,", 1976 August 16. (Folder 5: 27)
  - "A Most Dangerous Snake,", 1976 (Folder 5: 28)
  - "On Collecting Plants in the Tropics,", 1977 January. (Folder 5: 29)
  - "Pueblo, a Newspaper for the People" (re Costa Rican newspaper; written under pseudonym Larry Able), 1977 (Folder 5: 30)
    Typescript, transcript of interview with editor Javier Solís, and other working materials
  - Letter to the editor, Santa Rosa News-Herald, re monetary policy, 1978 August 12. (Folder 5: 31)
  - Letter to the editor, Santa Rosa Press-Democrat, re supermarket item-pricing (written on behalf of Gray Panthers), 1979 May 23. (Folder 5: 32)
  - "Agism: The Shunning of the Elderly,", 1979 (Folder 5)
    (book-length study, including multiple draft versions)
    - Outlines and front matter (Folder 5: 33)
    - Introduction (Folder 5: 34)
    - Chapter 1 (Folder 6: 1)
    - Chapter 2 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Chapter 3 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Chapter 4 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Chapter 5 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Chapter 6 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Chapter 7 (Folder 7: 1)
    - Chapter 8 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Chapter 9 (Folder 7: 3)
    - Footnotes and bibliography (Folder 7: 4)
    - Note card working materials (Folder 7: 5)
    - Correspondence with writer's agent Richard Curtis and publishers (Folder 7: 6)
  - "Fear of Aging in Children,", 1979 (Folder 7: 7)
    Outline and drafts for study never completed
  - "Collecting Plants in the Tropics for Your New York Home,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 7: 8)
  - "The Federal Reserve System: A Total Money-Making Machine,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 7: 9)
  - "The Great Redwood Park Hassle,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 7: 10)
  - "House Finches,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 7: 11)
  - "How Fawns Survive,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 7: 12)
  - "The Living Lakes of Yugoslavia,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 7: 13)
  - "Nature in the City,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 7: 14)
  - "On the Trail of a Hibernian Donkey,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 8: 1)
  - "The Redwoods in Spring,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 8: 2)
  - "Taste of Terror in the Night,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 8: 3)
  - "Three Weeds of Late Summer,", ca. 1970s. (Folder 8: 4)
  - "Why Doctors 'Play God,'", ca. 1970s. (Folder 8: 5)
  - Untitled memoir re father of Eric Hass, ca. 1970s. (Folder 8: 6)
  - Fragments, ca. 1970s (Folder 8: 7)
  - Remarks to Sonoma County, California, Board of Supervisors on behalf of Gray Panthers re supermarket item-pricing, 1980 (Folder 8: 8)
- Subject File, 1889-1980. (Folder 8-11)
  Notes, printed matter, correspondence, and typed copies, arranged alphabetically by topic
  - Aging (Folder 8)
    - General. Notes and mimeographed materials, 1977-1979 (Folder 8: 9)
    - Printed matter. Clippings and journal articles, 1943-1980 (Folder 8: 10-12)
    - Sources. Bibliographies and catalogs, 1977-1980 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Central America. Clippings and journal article, 1977-1978 (Folder 9: 1)
  - De Leon, Daniel (Folder 9)
    - Typed copies of De Leon correspondence, mainly with Olive M. Johnson, 1897-1913. (Folder 9: 2)
      Includes one photocopy of an original De Leon letter
    - Typed copies of De Leon writings, 1889-1913. (Folder 9: 3)
      Includes a few printed copies of articles, and pamphlet James Madison and Karl Marx
    - Correspondence about De Leon, 1933-1962, mainly from editorial files of The Weekly People. Includes letters by Arnold Petersen (Folder 9: 4)
    - Notes, clippings, and journal articles about De Leon, 1912-1977 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Environment and ecology. Clippings and journal articles, 1962-1977 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Gray Panthers (Folder 10)
  - General. Notes, lists, flyers, newsletters, circulated material, and clippings, 1975-1980 (Folder 10: 1)
  - Gray Panther Network issues, 1978-1980 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Imperialism. Notes, clippings, journal articles, and pamphlets, 1927-1967. (Folder 10: 3)
    Includes clippings from The Weekly People
  - Logging. Pamphlets, 1967 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Monetary policy and inflation. Clippings, journal articles, and other printed matter, 1925-1979 (Folder 10: 5)
  - Nature. Clippings and journal articles, 1958-1979 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Socialism. Clippings, journal articles, typed copies of journal articles, and other printed matter, 1910-1971, mainly re utopian socialist communities in the United States (Folder 11: 1)
  - Socialist Labor Party (Folder 11)
    - General. Notes, clippings, and typed copies of journal articles, 1900-1967 (Folder 11: 2)
    - Weekly People issues, 1967-1969 (Folder 11: 3-4)
  - Trinity Church (New York City). Leaflets, newsletters, minutes, and other printed matter, 1908-1979 (Folder 11: 5)
  - Wine. Typescript "The Glorious Grape" (authorship uncertain), 1978 (Folder 11: 6)
  - Yugoslavia. Tourist guide literature, and typed transcript of interview with I. Sharenow, 1970 (Folder 11: 7)
  - Miscellany. Mainly printed matter, 1946-1978 (Folder 11: 8)
- Audiovisual File, undated (Folder 11)
  Photographs
  - Photographs of Daniel De Leon, family, and associated locations (Folder 11: 9)
  - Photographs of Eric and Tillie Hass (Folder 11: 10)
  - Photographs of nature scenes (Folder 11: 11)
  - Photographs of Trinity Churchyard, New York City (Folder 11: 12)
  - Photographs of miscellaneous and unidentified scenes (Folder 11: 13)